RG 003, Hartford Housing Authority Investigation, Hartford Superior Court, One-man Grand Jury, Judge William Maltbie
Connecticut State Library
Hartford Housing Authority investigation records
circa 1940-1951
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Superior Court (Hartford County)
3.5 cubic feet
In the summer of 1951, State Supreme Justice William Mills Maltbie conducted a one-man grand jury investigation of the Hartford Housing Authority.
RG003_HHA
1987-064
Historical Note
The one man grand jury was the final stage of an investigation of the Hartford Housing Authority that began in 1950. In February, the Hartford Courant began publishing articles by reporter Gerald L. Demeusy about the Hartford Housing Authority and the conditions of the housing projects. Demeusy documented that trouble that large families had in getting a place in the housing projects. He learned that purchasing furniture from a certain store would constitute enough criteria to approve an application for housing. These exposes led the Hartford City Council to request that City Manager Carleton Sharpe conduct an investigation into the allegations against the HHA. Sharpe appointed a seven person Housing Board of Inquiry in April 1951. In late May, the Board began public hearings at which officials and employees of the HHA were questioned. It learned that individual members of the commission determined whose application for housing in the projects was approved, that its financial housekeeping was unprofessional and that contracts were given to only one architectural firm. In June 1951, before the Board ended its investigation, the Hartford Housing Authority Commission resigned en masse. This resulted in the termination of the investigation by the Housing Board of Inquiry. The Board submitted its report to the City Manager, citing the need for a "competent executive director" and a "trained staff" at the Hartford Housing Authority. Sharpe appointed four members of the Board of Inquiry to the Authority's commission.
However, serious questions about possible criminal behavior remained unanswered. For a couple weeks, Chief State's Attorney Albert S. Bill conducted an investigation with the assistance of the State Police. Governor John Davis Lodge recommended to Bill that he ask Hartford Superior Court Judge Thomas J. Molloy for the appointment of a one man grand jury to investigate the issues raised by the City of Hartford's inquiry. Molloy appointed the newly retired former Chief Justice of the State Supreme Court, William H. Maltbie, as a one man grand jury to "determine whether or not there is probable cause to believe that a crime or crimes have been committed within the county in connection with the affairs of the Housing Authority of the City of Hartford." In an editorial, the Hartford Courant praised the choice of Judge Maltbie, whom, it emphasized, "can be depended on for an impartial, judicial, and searching examination of the facts." "It is good that the matter has now reached this determinative stage," the Courant continued, "after all the previous detours, circumlocutions, and circumambulations." ("The Significant Phase of the Housing Inquiry," HC, July 12, 1951.)
Maltbie started his investigation on July 11 and examined documents and witnesses about the Authority's operations stretching back eight years. In his final report, the judge stated that he had "confined" his investigation to the period starting in September 1947 to June 1951. He had the power of subpoena and heard testimony in private with State's Attorney Bill participating in the questioning. At the same time State Auditors examined the Authority's business records, and their findings made the daily headlines. On October 18, Maltbie ended the taking of testimony from witnesses and on January 3, 1952, he issued a 16 page report of his findings. He found "no reasonable grounds for a prosecution for a crime," he did find "a lack of competence on the part of the commission and certain of its officers and employees" and "a lack of appreciation" by them of "their obligations to act fairly and disinterestedly in carrying on the large public service entrusted to them." ("Old HHA 'Controlled By Outside Influences' Says Maltbie; No Grounds For Prosecution," HC, January 4, 1952.) As the Courant concluded, "All is now past. But here it stands in the record as a warning, in the city and indeed in the State, that public office is still a public trust." ("The Verdict on the H.H.A.," HC, January 5, 1952.)
Scope and Content
The records consist of interviews; summonses; police material including reports and notebooks; correspondence; Hartford Housing Authority material; financial records including bank statements and cancelled checks, incorporation papers and tax returns; and newspaper clippings.
Arrangement
Series 1. Interviews, 1951. Arranged chronologically.
Series 2. Summonses, 1951. Arranged chronologically.
Series 3. Police Material, circa 1950-1951.
Series 4. Correspondence, circa 1940-1951. Arranged alphabetically
Series 5. Hartford Housing Authority, circa 1948-1951.
Series 6. Financial Records, circa 1940-1951.
Series 7. Newspaper Clippings, circa 1940-1951.
Related Material
RG005:032 John Davis Lodge Gubernatorial Records, box 577, Folder: Hartford Housing Authority.
Newspaper Clipping Files, 1932-1992, for the years 1950-1951.
Daniel Radcliffe, Charter Oak Terrace: Life, Death and Rebirth of a Housing Project”, 1998.
Index Terms
Organizations:
Connecticut. Superior Court (Hartford County); Hartford Housing Authority
Persons:
Beach, Goodwin Batterson; Dunn, Jacob; Gilligan, Edward; Kaminsky, E. Edward; Maltbie, William Mills, 1880-; Remer, George H.; Weiner, Abraham (Jack)
Places:
Hartford (Conn.)
Subjects:
Connecticut. Superior Court (Hartford County) -- Records and correspondence; Grand jury -- Connecticut -- Hartford County; Housing -- Connecticut -- Hartford; Investigations
Document Types:
Articles of incorporation; Bank statements; Checks (bank checks); Clippings; Contracts; Correspondence; Judicial Records; Minutes; Notebooks; Purchase orders; Receipts (financial records); Reports; Summonses; Tax returns; Transcripts
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Container List
- Series 1. Interviews, 1951
  - Summaries and index, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - O'Neil, John J, 1951 July 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Stavol, James D., 1951 July 5 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rosenthal, Ernest, 1951 July 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Weiner, Abraham J. (Jack), 1951 July 6 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Doyle, John F., 1951 July 6 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Metropoils, Thomas, 1951 July 9 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Galic, Harold E., 1951 July 9 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ames Construction Company (Defazio, Pasqualle and Ferizzi, Frank), 1951 July 9 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Roog, Joseph, 1951 July 9 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Johnson, Mary, 1951 July 10 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Murray, Mary, 1951 July 10 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Giardini, Angelo, 1951 July 11 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Williams, Antone M., 1951 July 11 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Demers, Albert, 1951 July 12 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Scott, William A., 1951 July 12 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Gillespie, Rufus, 1951 July 12 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hart, Edmond (Edward), 1951 July 13 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Pearson, John, 1951 July 16 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Donohue, Michael, 1951 July 18 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Putnam, Rosalind Lawson, 1951 July 18 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - French, Lawrence, 1951 July 18 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Fletcher, Daniel, 1951 July 19 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - McManus, Barbara F., 1951 July 19 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Lee, Ann M., 1951 July 19 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cardo, Joseph Anthony, 1951 July 20 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Camillieri, Joseph, 1951 July 20 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Spitzer, Henry, 1951 July 23 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Ludorf, Henry F., 1951 July 23 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Vercelli, Joseph T., 1951 July 24 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Scheide, Lester Beach, 1951 July 25 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Marshall, Harold B., 1951 July 25 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Gosselin, U. D., 1951 July 26 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Anderson, Joseph F., 1951 July 26 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Bidwell, Harold Frederick, 1951 July 26 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Erff, Frederick, 1951 July 27 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - McQuade, Thomas J., 1951 August 2 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - O'Neil, Thomas J., 1951 August 2, 6 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Turley, Vincent E., 1951 August 7 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Gilligan, Edward W., 1951 August 8 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Gregory, George, 1951 August 14 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Hills, Russell, 1951 August 21 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Goulet, Gerard C., 1951 August 21 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Weinburg, Leo G., 1951 August 22 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Tramonte, Emil, 1951 August 22 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Cohen, Sally B., 1951 August 28 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Beidelman, Elanor, 1951 August 28 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Manaker, Aaron, 1951 August 28 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Gilbertson, Mary S., 1951 August 29 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Hyman, George M., circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Beach, Goodwin B., circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Kane, Joseph E., circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dunn, Jacob, circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Loshbough, Bernard E., circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Kaminski, E. Edward, circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Simons, Rubin, circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Barry, John T., circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - McDonough, Charles, circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - McCue, William D., circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Fairchild, Henry, circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Kelly, John P., circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Roth Hardware (Harry Rosenthal), circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Kane, John (Boston), circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Index to testamony, circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Series 2. Summonses, 1951
  - Doyle, John F, 1951 July 16 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - O'Neil, John J., 1951 July 16 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Remer, Lt. George H., 1951 July 16 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Stavol, James D., 1951 July 16 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Defazio, Pasqualle, 1951 July 18 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Feriuzzi, Frank, 1951 July 18 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Gallic, Harold E., 1951 July 18 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Metropoils, Thomas, 1951 July 18 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Pearson, John B., 1951 July 18 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Rosenthal, Ernest, 1951 July 20 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Weiner, Abraham J. (Jack), 1951 July 20 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Spitzer, Henry, 1951 July 23 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Demers, Albert C., 1951 July 24 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - McCook, Anson T., 1951 July 24 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Scott, William A., 1951 July 24 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Williams, Antone M., 1951 July 24 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Cardo, Joseph Anthony, 1951 July 25 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Giardini, Angelo, 1951 July 25 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Hart, Edward J., 1951 July 25 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Roog, Joseph, 1951 July 25 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - The Hartford Metal Products Company, Inc., 1951 July 30 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - The Hartford Roofing and Sheet Metal Company, Inc., 1951 July 30 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Hyman, George M., 1951 July 30 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Fairchild, Henry, 1951 July 30 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Kane, Joseph E., 1951 July 30 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Kane and Fairchild, Architechts (a partnership), 1951 July 30 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - The White Company, Inc., 1951 July 30 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Fletcher, Daniel, 1951 August 22 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - French, Lawrence Theron, 1951 August 22 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Gillespie, Rufus Charles, 1951 August 22 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Putnam, Rosalind Lawson, 1951 August 22 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Loshbough, Bernard E., 1951 August 22, 23 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - McDonough, Charles H., 1951 August 22, 23 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Anderson, Joseph F., 1951 August 24, 28 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Bidwell, Harold Frederick, 1951 August 24, 28 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Camillieri, Joseph F., 1951 August 24 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Donohue, Michael, 1951 August 24 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Gosselin, U. D., 1951 August 24 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Ludorf, Henry F., 1951 August 24 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Marshall, Harold W., 1951 August 24 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Scheide, Lester Beach, 1951 August 24 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Vercelli, Joseph T., 1951 August 24 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Purrington, Wilbur, 1951 August 28 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Cohen, Sally B., 1951 August 30 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Goulet, Gerard C., 1951 August 30 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Gregory, George M., 1951 August 30 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Lee, Ann M., 1951 August 30 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - McManus, Barbara F., 1951 August 30 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - McQuade, Thomas J., 1951 August 30 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - O'Neil, Thomas J., 1951 August 30 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Tramonte, Emil, 1951 August 30 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Turley, Vincent E., 1951 August 30 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Weinburg, Leo G., 1951 August 30 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Michel, Sam, 1951 September 4 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Kane, Joseph E., 1951 September 6 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Barry, John T., 1951 September 7 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Beach, Goodwin B., 1951 September 7 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Carr, George E., 1951 September 7 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Kaminski, E. Edward, 1951 September 7 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Manaker, Aaron, 1951 September 7 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Barry, John T., 1951 September 12 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Hart, Owen, 1951 September 12 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Brown, Warren M., 1951 September 21 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Gilligan, Edward W., 1951 September 21 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Hills, Russell, 1951 September 21 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - McCue, William D., 1951 September 21 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Simon, Philip, 1951 September 21 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Rosenthal, Harry, 1951 September 25 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Kane, John, 1951 September 28 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Bailey, John M., 1951 October 5 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Dunn, Jacob, 1951 October 5 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Kelly, John P., 1951 October 5 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Murphy, Thomas E., 1951 October 9 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Galleraini, Margurite, 1951 October 17 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Series 3. Police Material, circa 1950-1951
  - Reports (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Officer Miller, Lois F., 1951 July (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Lt. Remer, George H., circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Notebooks (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Officer Doyle, John J., circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Officer Leonard, Thomas, circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Lt. Remer, George H., 1951 June (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Detective Rome, Samuel (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - 1951 June 25-July 3 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - 1951 July 23-August 8 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Unidentified police books and loose pages, circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Unidentified steno books, circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Lt. George H. Remer material, circa 1951 (Box 2)
    This material appears to be from the desk of Lt. George H. Remer.
    - Correspondance, Number 1 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Indexes, Number 2 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Notes, Number 3 of 3 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Court documents, circa 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Notes, circa 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Series 4. Correspondence, circa 1940-1951
  - Annonymous information, circa 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Architect's materials, circa 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Barry, John T., circa 1940-1951 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Gallic, Harold E., circa 1940-1951 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Fleige, Harold, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Goulet material, circa 1940-1951 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Kane and Fairchild miscellaneous papers, circa 1940-1951 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - McCook, Anson T., circa 1948 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - O'Neil, John J. miscellaneous papers, circa 1940-1951 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Roofing quote, 1950 April (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Stavol, James D. material, circa 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - J. S. Thorn, Co., 1950 May 5 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Tramonte, Emil, circa 1940-1951 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Turley, Vincent E. suspension and reinstatement letter, 1951 May (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Series 5. Hartford Housing Authority, circa 1948-1951
  - Part 1 of 4: Court papers, circa 1951 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Part 2 of 4: Correspondance, circa 1951 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Part 3 of 4: Sharpe inquiry, circa 1951 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Part 4 of 4: Notes, circa 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - List of personnel, circa 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Reports, circa 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Attorney and architect's contracts, circa 1948-1951 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Extracts of minutes SHA, 1949, May 23 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Series 6. Financial Records, circa 1940-1951
  - Bond list for Charles McDonough, Inc, circa 1948-1951 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Bank statements, Joseph and Lillian Kane, 1948-1951 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Cancelled checks (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Hartford Roofing, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Joseph and Lillian Kane (Box 3)
      - 1947 December-1948 April (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - 1948 May-September (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - 1948 October-December (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - 1950 November-1951 March (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - 1951 April-June (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - 1948-1951 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - C. H. McDonough, Inc, circa 1940-1951 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Jack Weiner, circa 1945 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Incorporation papers (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Barry Square Real Estate and Insurance, Inc, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Charles McDonough, Inc, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - General Freight System, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Norwood Development, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Seven Thirty Four Corp., 1950 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - The White Company, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Pickup truck owned by Hartford Housing Authority, circa 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Rent receipts, Hartford Housing Authority, 1948, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Tax returns (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - General Freight System, 1948-1950 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Charles McDonough, Inc, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Norwood Development, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - The White Company, 1949-1950 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Purchase orders, Hartford Housing Authority, 1946-1947 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Unidentified ledger sheets, 1951 May-June (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series 7. Newspaper Clippings, circa 1940-1951
  - Newspaper clippings, circa 1940-1951 (Box 4, Folder 9)